<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>New-Englands sence, of Old-England and Jrelands sorrowes a sermon preached upon a day of generall humiliation in the churches of New-England : in the behalfe of Old-England and Jrelands sad condition / by William Hooke ...</title>
            <author>Hooke, William, 1600 or 1601-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44327</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2623</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10758</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12198946</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12198946</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56068</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44327)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56068)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 763:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>New-Englands sence, of Old-England and Jrelands sorrowes a sermon preached upon a day of generall humiliation in the churches of New-England : in the behalfe of Old-England and Jrelands sad condition / by William Hooke ...</title>
                  <author>Hooke, William, 1600 or 1601-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Rothwell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preached probably on April 14, 1642.--cf. JCB, 1919, II, 331, and Church 470.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Samuel, 2nd. --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fasts and feasts --  Massachusetts.</term>
               <term>Sermons, American --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56068:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56068:1"/>
            <p>New-Englands Sence, OF OLD-ENGLAND AND JRELANDS SORROWES.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached upon a day of generall Humiliation in the Churches of NEW-ENGLAND. In the behalfe of <hi>Old-England</hi> and <hi>Jrelands</hi> Sad condition. By WILLIAM HOOKE, Miniſter of GODS Word at <hi>Taunton</hi> in NEVV-ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>Intruſted in the hands of a worthy Member of the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſe of Commons, who deſired it might be Printed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur</hi> JOSEPH CARYL.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>John Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ell,</hi> at the Signe of the <hi>Sunne</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi>-Church-yard, 1645.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56068:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56068:2"/>
            <head>NEW ENGLANDS SENCE, OF OLD ENGLAND, AND IRELANDS SORROWES.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 SAM: 10.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> And when the children of <hi>Ammon</hi> ſaw that they ſtank before <hi>David,</hi> the children of <hi>Ammon</hi> ſent and hired the <hi>Syrians</hi> of <hi>Beth-Rehob,</hi> and the <hi>Syrians</hi> of <hi>Zoba,</hi> twenty thouſand footmen, and of King <hi>Maacha</hi> a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men, and of <hi>Iſhtob</hi> twelve thouſand footmen.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> And when <hi>David</hi> heard of it, he ſent <hi>Ioab,</hi> and all the hoſt of the mighty m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> And the Children of <hi>Ammon</hi> came out, and put the battle in array at the entring in of the gate: and the <hi>Syrians</hi> of <hi>Zoba,</hi> and of <hi>Rehob,</hi> and <hi>Iſhtob,</hi> and <hi>Maacah, were</hi> by themſelves in the field.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> When <hi>Ioab</hi> ſaw that the front of the battle was againſt him before and behind, he choſe of all the choice men of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and put them in array againſt the <hi>Syrians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10</hi> And the reſt of the people he delivered into the hand of <hi>Abiſhai</hi> his brother, that he might put them in array againſt the children of <hi>Ammon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11</hi> And he ſaid, If the <hi>Syrians</hi> be too ſtrong for me, then thou ſhalt helpe me: but if the children of <hi>Ammon</hi> be too ſtrong for thee, then I will come and helpe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12</hi> Bee of good courage, and let us play the men, for our people, and the Cities of our God; and the Lord doe that which ſeemeth him good.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He occaſion of this warrs was this. <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſh</hi> the King of <hi>Ammon</hi> (he who once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the right eyes of the <hi>Gileadites,</hi> and to lay it as a reproach upon all <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> upon condition of covenanting with them) is
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56068:3"/>now dead. He had been, it ſeemes, a friend to <hi>David,</hi> in oppoſition, probably, to <hi>Saul</hi> who was an enemy to them both. <hi>David</hi> looked at the expreſſions of his love, and left his heart to him that ſearched it, accounting it an office of humanity to comfort him concerning the death of his Father. His kindneſſe is miſconſtrued by the Princes of the children of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> who detracting from the ſyncere intentions of upright <hi>David,</hi> haſten to their King and fill him full of jealouſie and prejudice againſt <hi>David,</hi> as if he had not ſent Embaſſadors, but Spies; not Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but Traytors. The young King is overthrowne in the entrance of his government by evill Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, whoſe ſuggeſtions he receives in ſtead of the comfort of <hi>Davids</hi> Embaſſadors, which coſt him deare. His Counſellors were indeed his Traytors, not the Meſſengers. Alas, how fearefully is the King miſguided in the threſhold of his raigne, by ſuch who ſhould have better adviſed him? It is well ſaid of a Byſhop upon theſe words; <hi>Happie is that State, where both the Counſellors are faithfull to give onely good advice, and the King wiſe to diſcerne good advice from evill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what doth <hi>Hanun</hi> doe? He takes the ſervants of <hi>David</hi> and ſhaves off the one half of their beards, and cuts off their garments in the middle, and ſends them away. The newes of it is brought to <hi>David,</hi> who ſends to meet them; becauſe they were greatly aſhamed, and he ſaid, Tarry at <hi>Iericho</hi> untill your beards be growne, and then returne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And when the children of</hi> Ammon <hi>ſaw that they
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56068:3"/>ſtanke before</hi> David, <hi>they ſent and hired the Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words, there is, firſt, A preparation for warr by the <hi>Ammonites</hi> againſt <hi>David.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Davids</hi> addreſſing himſelfe for an encounter.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Ammons</hi> preparations, there is, Firſt, The ground of it, which was; <hi>becauſe they ſaw that they ſtanke before David.</hi> Secondly, The hyring of <hi>Auxiliaries</hi> out of <hi>Syria,</hi> and that at a deare rate, <hi>viz. For a thouſand talents of ſilver,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.6.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Davids</hi> addreſſe for encounter, we have, firſt, his ſending of <hi>Ioab,</hi> with all the hoſt of the mighty men. Secondly, The ſubtiltie of the <hi>Ammonites,</hi> who were ſo wiſe as to devide their forces, and to leave the <hi>Syrians</hi> to fight in the open fields, whom they durſt not truſt at the entrance in of their Cities, while themſelves put the battaile in array before the gates, that ſo alſo they might (if need were) have opportunity to retire. Thirdly, The wiſdome of <hi>Ioab</hi> in ordering the battell the beſt way, in the ſtrait he was in. Fourthly, a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of mutuall aſſiſtance between <hi>Ioab</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhai,</hi> as need ſhould require. Fiftly, <hi>Ioabs</hi> words of encouragement to <hi>Abiſhai,</hi> yea and to himſelfe. <hi>Be of good courage, &amp; let us play the men, &amp;c.</hi> Which are the words that I have eſpecially lookt at for the occaſion of this day. But ſome things I ſhall briefly obſerve in the way to them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the ground of <hi>Ammons</hi> preparations; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>They ſaw that they did ſtinke before</hi> David, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56068:4"/>of the abuſe they had done to his Embaſſadors. Whence we may obſerve.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſervation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Indignities and inhumane carriages to Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors of Peace, is that which will make the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of GOD to ſtinke in the noſtrils of his People.</p>
            <p>Doe not expect a parallel text for proofe, for ſuch practices have bin very rare till of later yeres. There is no ſinne but it ſtinkes in the noſtrils of God, but as for men, it muſt be very groſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it hath ſo ill a ſavour; and ſuch are eſpecially groſie ſinnes againſt the ſecond Table, as being committed againſt the greater light. Of this kind I remember for the preſent but one more in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and that was the bloody treachery of <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> againſt the <hi>Sechemites,</hi> to whom there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Father <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaid, <hi>Yee have made me to ſtinke among the inhabitants of the land,</hi> Gen. 34.30. For ſuch dealings are againſt the light of blindeſt nature, eſpecially ſuch uſage of Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, whoſe name hath ever bin honourable by the law of Nations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, This gives us to ſee one ſpeciall cauſe why the Prelats in <hi>England</hi> doe this day ſtinke in the roſtrils of Gods people, yea of many ſuch as have but little Religion in them, there indignities and abuſes offered to the Lords Embaſſadors have bin infinite and intollerable. Alas! what are the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolencies of <hi>Hanun</hi> here, to theirs? For firſt, He
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56068:4"/>and his <hi>Ammonites</hi> never ſaw the tythe of that light that theſe have done. <hi>Ammon</hi> ſaw not the light of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> nor <hi>Iſrael</hi> the light of <hi>England.</hi> Secondly, thoſe indignities done by <hi>Hanun,</hi> were farre inferiour unto theſe. For firſt, He onely cut the beards and garments of theſe Meſſengers, whoſe beards grew out againe at <hi>Iericho,</hi> and whoſe gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments might be changed for longer; whereas theſe have pared the Eares of the ſervants of God, which can never grow againe; and ſtigmatized the Faces with indelible characters. And therefore, ſecondly, <hi>Hanun</hi> came not ſo neare to the perſons of thoſe Meſſengers, for hee medled onely with beards and garments, the cutting off of which ſhed no blood; whereas theſe have offered bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy indignities to the Lords Embaſſadors. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thoſe <hi>Ammonitiſh</hi> inſolencies brought upon Meſſengers onely a civill inconformity in hayre and veſtments to the manners of Gods Iſrael: whereas the practiſes of theſe men have forced a Spirituall conformity on Gods Miniſters, to the manners of that great Strumpet and Mother of whoredomes. Fourthly, <hi>Davids</hi> meſſengers were abuſed onely in Beards and Garments; but theſe have been Convented, Suſpended, Deprived, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graded, Exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated, Impriſoned, Impillored, Fined, ſtript of all, Exiled, and expoſed to great extremities. Thus the indignities conſidered in themſelves were farre inferiour unto theſe. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Hanun</hi> never ſinned herein againſt Conſcience, as theſe have done; for he was miſguided by his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56068:5"/>Princes, and ſo hee knew not that the Meſſengers were Spies: whereas the Prelats have offered horrible indignities to many ſuch of whoſe inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie they have themſelves firſt given ample teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. Fourthly, <hi>Hanum</hi> did nothing obſtinatly, for his Nobles perſwaded him; but with theſe, all the Noble men in the land could not prevaile with that <hi>Arch-Ammonite</hi> and his followers, to deale favourably with the Lords Embaſſadors. Fiftly, If we looke upon the Meſſengers, <hi>Hanuns</hi> inhumanitie was offered to the meſſengers of a mortall Prince, but theſe men have moſt dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully abuſed the Embaſſadors of the Prince of the Kings of the Earth. For the Lord hath ſent his Meſſengers to <hi>England,</hi> and one they have beaten, another they have killed, a third they have ſtoned; or that which is as bad. Againe, the Lord hath ſent more Servants, and they have done to them likewiſe. Laſtly, thoſe were ſent only to miniſter a little comfort to a man who (it ſeemes) had no great need of it; but theſe have been ſent to publiſh the Goſpell of everlaſting Peace to the wearied.</p>
            <p>O monſters among men that theſe Prelats are, trained up by Tygers, whom no inceſtuous of-ſpring of <hi>Lot</hi> can parallel by a thouſand degrees! that if ſuch Prodigies among men doe this day ſtinke in the noſtrils, not of <hi>Iſraelites</hi> onely, but even <hi>Ammonites</hi> alſo, wee have great cauſe of thankfulneſſe, none of wonder.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, This may ſhew us the ſad eſtate of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56068:5"/>theſe noiſome enemies of CHRIST and his Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; for ſeeing they are thus unſavory, what are they good for? What uſe can there be made of unſavory Salt? It is neither fit, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>for the Land, nor for the Dung-hill.</hi> It is good, ſaith he, for nothing, but to be caſt out, and troden un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot of men, <hi>Math.</hi> 5.13. An unſavory <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monite</hi> may be good either for the land or for the dung hill. <hi>Moah</hi> was troden downe as ſtraw for the dung-hill, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.10. But an unſavory Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late is good for neither, as being unſavorie Salt. The moſt noiſome Dung that is, is good enough for the dung-hill; but unſavory Salt is not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſo farre from making barren land fruit-full, that it makes fruit full land barren. And ſuch ſalt are the enemies of CHRISTS Embaſſadors, that where-ever a Prelate hath been caſt, the place (though fruit full before) hath ſoone proved bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren in Religion round about him. For as they have no favour of life in themſelves, they cannot endure either that Miniſter or People that have: Oh what will become of them now, whom the very dunghill doth reject? Who ſhall lament for them now, ſaying, Ah my brother; or, ah Lord; or, ah his glory, when they ſhall be caſt forth beyond the gates of <hi>Ieruſalem?</hi> As for other men, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo vile, or degenerous, that are ſtill good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for the dunghill; men will find ſome mean imployment or other to put them to. If there be refuſe people in a land, thou ſhalt have a drumme beaten up to call them together, that they may be
<pb facs="tcp:56068:6"/>ſent forth in ſome ſervice againſt the enemies of the land: whereas theſe want both ability and fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity for ſuch a ſervice. Yea, ſhould they come and crouch for a piece of ſilver, or a morſell of bread, ſaying, put us into the Prieſts Office, or as it is rendred after the Original, put us into ſomewhat about the Prieſthood, as much as to ſay, make Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Clarks of us, that we may eat a peece of bread; they are not fit for it, for they cannot ſay, <hi>Amen,</hi> to the prayers of Gods people this day. They are not fit to occupy any roome in <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Common wealth;</hi> they are not fit for Pulpit, or Preſſe, for Church-government, Counſell-Table, Parliament, Iuſticeſhip, Traffique, who have thus long traded onely for the mother of Whoredome, and who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin now to weepe and mourne, <hi>becauſe no man buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth their Marchandiſe any more, Revel.</hi> 18. 11. They are not then good for warre, nor peace; for Prince, not people; for Church nor State: onely being wiſer in their Generation, then the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of light, like that wicked Steward they have robbed and ſpoiled, and feathered their neſts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were turned out of their Stewardſhips, as being conſcious to themſelves, that digge I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, and to begg they are aſhamed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, This ſhould make us this day more earneſt with God for <hi>England,</hi> that he would purge the Land of this filth; for otherwiſe how noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome will that Countrey be wherein there are ſo many unſavory creatures. Not that we deſire any other purging of them, then their depoſing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56068:6"/>for their horrible indig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aties, and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ities to the Embaſſadours of the King of Kings. And thus much for the grounds of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> Preparations to muſter up Forces againſt <hi>David,</hi> becauſe they ſaw, <hi>that they ſtanke before him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, we have their hiring of <hi>Auxiliaries</hi> to defend them in their wickedueſſe: <hi>They ſent and hyred the Syrians</hi> of Beth Rehob, <hi>and the Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of</hi> Zoba, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſervation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When wicked men are come to that height of ſinne, that they ſtinck in the noſtrils of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they will rather dye, then confeſſe and repent of their wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>We have the like example in the <hi>Benjamites</hi> againſt the eleven Tribes. And it is made good this day in the Prelates againſt <hi>England.</hi> For wheras they ſhould have put on ſackcloth on their loines, and ropes upon their necks, and gone to the King and Parliament, ſaying; <hi>Your ſervants ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pray you let us live;</hi> they have ſtood out rebelliouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and proteſted againſt Parliamentary procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. Nay, their monies have gone moſt profuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the hiring of <hi>Syrians,</hi> and the maintenance of warres againſt the <hi>Scots,</hi> calling it, <hi>Bellum Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pale; The Biſhops Warre.</hi> It was 1000. talents of ſilver that the <hi>Ammonites</hi> expended to hire helpe againſt the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, when firſt they had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred them ſuch a mouſtrous indignity: But how many thouſand talents theſe have disburſed and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56068:7"/>collected among themſelves, and their Clergy, and Popiſhly affected partie, it is not eaſie for to ſay. For, <hi>The Angell of the Lord hath powered out his vi-all upon their Sun, and they have been ſcorched with great heat, and have blaſphemed the name of the Lord which hath power over theſe Plagues; and they have not repented to give him glory.</hi> REV. 16. 8. 9.</p>
            <p>But whom now doe the <hi>Ammonites</hi> hire? but a ſort of flagitious <hi>Pagans,</hi> that neither looked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the price of other mens blood, their own ſoules, or the juſtneſſe of the cauſe? A thouſand talents have ſoone bought them to fight the battels of the Devill againſt the Lord of Hoſts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſervation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no cauſe ſo wicked or deplored, but money will hire ſome mercinarily minded to abet, who wil damne their ſoules for a little ſilver. And how many ſuch there have been even in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world, the Prelates better know then wee. What forlorne creatures, <hi>Papiſts, Atheiſts, Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> and <hi>mongrell Proteſtants,</hi> had they procured to fight againſt the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nation? When wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men are conſcious to the inſufficiency of their cauſe, they muſter up the greater forces, and place their affiance in the arme of fleſh; that what inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence here could not doe, three and thirty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>Pagans</hi> joyned to the forces of <hi>Ammon</hi> ſhall. But thus much ſhall ſuffice to be ſpoken of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> Preparations, both their ground and helps.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, in <hi>Davids</hi> providing to encounter them, we have, Firſt, his ſending of <hi>Ioab,</hi> with all
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56068:7"/>the Hoſt of the mighty men. <hi>David,</hi> you ſee, is ſencible of the horrible abuſes done to his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſervation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indignities offered to Embaſſadors, redound to their King, who cannot be inſenſible thereof, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, they being Embaſſadours of Peace.</p>
            <p>And thus it is with God; as it is written, <hi>The Lord God of their Fathers ſent to them by his meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, riſing up betimes, and ſending, becauſe he had compaſsion on his people, and on his dwelling place: but they mocked the Meſſengers of God, and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his words, and miſuſed his Prophets, untill the wrath of the Lord aroſe, and there was no remedy. Therefore he brought upon them the King of the</hi> Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees, <hi>who ſlew the young men with the ſword in the houſe of their Sanctuary, and had no compaſsion upon young man or may den, old man, or him that ſtooped for age; he gave them all unto his hand.</hi> 2 Chro. 36. 15, 16, 17. And now under the Goſpell; <hi>when the Lord of the Vineyard ſends his ſervants to the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen, and the Husbandmen beat one, and kill an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and ſtone a third; and when hee ſends yet more ſervants, and they doe unto them likewiſe; ſurely he will miſerably deſtroy thoſe wicked men, and will let out his Vineyard to other Husbandmen, which ſhall render him the fruits in their ſeaſon.</hi> Matth. 21. 33.</p>
            <p>Belo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed! CHRIST is this day ſenſible of all the abuſes that have been offered by the Prelats to his Meſſengers. How often hath he cryed from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56068:8"/>if that poore ſoule had not been utterly deafe, <hi>Laud, Laud, Why perſecuteſt thou me? It is hard for thee to kicke againſt the pricks.</hi> Oh! CHRIST in his Meſſengers hath given his back to the ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and his cheeks to them that have plucked off the haire; his beard hath beene cut, and his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments curtold by theſe Prelatique <hi>Ammonites.</hi> The Meſſengers of <hi>Ieſus</hi> have bin made a ſpectacle to the world, Angels, and men; they have beene made partakers of Chriſts ſufferings, and have fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led up that which is behind of the afflictions of Chriſt in their fleſh, for his bodies ſake which is the Church. And is Chriſt ſenſible, and ſhall not theſe <hi>Ammonites</hi> heare of it? Yes; for he is now awaking as out of ſleep, and like a mighty man that ſhouteth by reaſon of Wine; Ah! ſaith hee, <hi>I will eaſe me of mine adverſaries, and avenge me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of mine enemies, and put them to perpetuall ſhame.</hi> But ſo much be ſaid of this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioab</hi> now approaching with his Forces; when loe, the Adverſaries have cunningly devided them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſome ſtanding at the entrance of the gates of the Citie, the reſidue in the open field. <hi>Ioab</hi> a wiſe Generall, and prepared for difficulties, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſteth the beſt way of encounter, and fitting himſelfe to aſſault the <hi>Syrians,</hi> leaves the <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monities</hi> to his brother <hi>Abiſhai,</hi> but with this co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of mutuall aſſiſtance (for I muſt now put ſundry things together) <hi>If the Syrians be too ſtrong for me, then thou ſhalt help me, but if the Children of Ammon be too ſtrong for thee, then will I come and help thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:56068:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſervation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When Gods <hi>Iſrael</hi> hath to doe with many po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, ſubtill, moſt wicked and deſperate enemies, they had need to enter into a covenant of mutuall helpe and aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abraham</hi> was confederate with <hi>Mamre, Eſchol,</hi> and <hi>Aner,</hi> when hee was to encounter with the foure Kings that had carryed away his couſen <hi>Lot,</hi> priſoner, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. 13. 24. Yea, it is lawfull for us herein to learne wit of an enemy; For thus the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of <hi>Iſrael</hi> confederate themſelves. <hi>Come,</hi> ſay they, <hi>let us cut them off from being a Nation, that the name of Iſrael may bee no more in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</hi> Yea, they have conſulted together with one conſent, and are confederate againſt <hi>Iſrael;</hi> the Tabernacles of <hi>Edom,</hi> and the <hi>Iſhmaelites,</hi> of <hi>Moah,</hi> and the <hi>Hagarens, Gebal,</hi> and <hi>Ammon,</hi> and <hi>Amalech,</hi> the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> with the inhabitants of <hi>Tyre; Aſſur</hi> alſo is joyned with them, they have holpen the children of <hi>Lot, Pſal.</hi> 83. 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9. And in the daies of <hi>Ahaz</hi> it was told the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Syria is confederate with Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im, Iſa.</hi> 7. 2.</p>
            <p>And this covenanting in caſe of oppoſing many, powerfull, cunning, wicked, deſperate Enemies, is very requiſite; <hi>Seeing a Kingdome divided cannot ſtand,</hi> which firmely united by confederacie is not eaſily vanquiſhed, when every mans intereſſes are anothers, and the ſame ingagements common unto all. And this <hi>Antichriſt</hi> knowes well enough; for hee being ſet forth moſt lively
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56068:9"/>under the Type of <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> in the 11.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Daniel,</hi> his heart is ſaid to be <hi>againſt the holy Covenant, verſ.</hi> 28. by and by hee is ſaid to have intelligence with them <hi>that forſake the holy Covenant;</hi> yea, and to have <hi>indignation againſt the holy Covenant, verſ.</hi> 30. And ſuch as doe wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, againſt the Covenant, He is ſaid, <hi>to corrupt by flatteries, verſ.</hi> 32. Marke theſe expreſſions. His heart is againſt the <hi>holy Covenant.</hi> His very heart riſeth at the name of <hi>Covenant,</hi> and <hi>Covenanting,</hi> and <hi>Covenanters,</hi> and thoſe are the moſt odious people with him in all the world. Yea, he hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt the <hi>holy Covenant.</hi> Hee could teare it in his teeth; the very gall of bitterneſſe ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in him at it. And with whom hath he intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, but with them that forſake it? They are his Counſellours, that either fall off from the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, or are learned to declaime and raile againſt it. And ſuch as doe wickedly againſt the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> he corrupteth by flatteries. If there be any who are more malicious then others againſt the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and the <hi>Covenanters,</hi> who will goe about to breake the League, to raiſe Armes, to hatch Treaſons, to confound Kingdomes, Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths and Parliaments, and to bring all things into combuſtion, that he may fiſh in troubled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, O theſe are his white boyes, theſe he ſmooths and ſtroakes, and flatters, theſe ſhall have Preben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries, Biſhopticks, Cardinals Caps, and great preferments, &amp;c. And no marvaile, for theſe <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters</hi> is the ruine of <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> for he could
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56068:9"/>never have beene, if the <hi>Covenant</hi> had beene kept, his <hi>Babel</hi> can never be built where men keep cloſe to God and one another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, this ſheweth us the wonderfull goodneſſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> of God in foure particulars, which ſhould melt our hearts this day.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in uniting the Honourable Nation of the <hi>Scots</hi> by Covenant againſt the Prelates, in their late defence againſt their Tyranny. Which how powerfull and ſucceſſefull it was, we may eaſily ſee, not onely by the carriage and iſſue of things on their parts, but alſo by the continuall attempts of the Prelates to have devided them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In the firme brotherly Union of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> as it were of <hi>Joab</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhai;</hi> and that too, by ſuch an occaſion, as the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates hoped ſhould have engaged them in blood, the one againſt the other, like <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> againſt <hi>Ephraim,</hi> or as if <hi>Ioab</hi> and <hi>Abiſhai</hi> ſhould cut one anothers throats.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In uniting both houſes of Parliament, they having to do with ſuch <hi>Ammonites</hi> and <hi>Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> It is ſuch a knot, that the very Sword of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> we hope, ſhall not eaſily cut aſunder.</p>
            <p>A Kingdome united into one body, will endure a mighty ſhock. Men ſtanding ſingle are ſoone juſled downe, moſt difficult, when they are all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodied into one.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, In uniting the hearts of all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in this Land to one another, and all of them
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56068:10"/>this day to our deare Countrey, in oppoſing the common Adverſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r what hath <hi>England</hi> ſaid to us of late? <hi>If the Papi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s, Prelats, and Atheiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s be too ſtrong for us, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n you ſhall help us;</hi> and <hi>if at any time the enemy be too ſtrong for you, wee will help you.</hi> O let us all enter into Covenant with <hi>England,</hi> to live and dye againſt theſe <hi>Ammonites</hi> and <hi>Syrians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, If ſo neceſſary bee a Covenant of mutuall aſſiſtance againſt a common Enemy, ſuch a one as we heare of; how much more had the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> of God, need to enter into Covenant with the Lord of Hoſts, in oppoſing ſuch an Adverſary. What is a Politicke to a Religious Covenant? When the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> fled, and fell before the men of <hi>Ai;</hi> the Lord gives the reaſon of it unto <hi>Ioſhua, Ioſh.</hi> 7.11. <hi>Iſrael hath finned, and they have tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed my Covenant which I commanded them; for they have taken of the accurſed thing, &amp;c.</hi> Where by the way, you may ſee how neerely this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant uniteth, that what one doth, (which the reſt might with circumſpection have prevented) is imputed to them all. The Lord will never have need to ſay to <hi>England,</hi> or to us, If the Malignant party with their Cavaliers be too ſtrong for mee, then ſhall you help me; but we ſhall have need ſo to ſay to him; and therefore wee had need ſee that we be in covenant with him.</p>
            <p>And where a people are in Covenant with God, and cleave onely to him, having caſt away whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is diſpleaſing to him, hee enters himſelfe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56068:10"/>preſently the Generall of all their forces, leades their Armies, and fights their Battails. And then who can bee againſt us? For one ſhall chaſe a thouſand, and ten, ten thouſand; becauſe their Rock will not fell them, nor the Lord ſhut them up. And ſo much for the Covenant of mutuall aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>We are now come to <hi>Ioabs</hi> words of Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement: wherein we have; Firſt, an Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Secondly, a Reſignation. An exhortation to be Valiant in fighting the Lords Battels; and a Reſignation of their wills into the Lords hands.</p>
            <p>Firſt, of the Exhortation. <hi>Be of good courage, and let us play the men for our people, &amp; for the Cities of our God.</hi> And here we may obſerve the grounds of their encouragement, <hi>viz.</hi> They were to fight for all that they had, or were; God, and their Countrey; Church, and State; ſoules and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; their owne, and others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſervations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When Religion and Policie, Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth lye at ſtake, Gods people had need to encourage themſelves, and one another.</p>
            <p>Therefore we ſhall finde, that when the people of God were to go to battell againſt his enemies, both the Lords, the Prieſts, and the Officers, did (<hi>All</hi>) give them encouragement, <hi>Deut.</hi> 20.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9. The place is pregnant to this purpoſe, and worthy our reading. Excellent are the words of <hi>Nehemiah</hi> to this point, <hi>Neh.</hi> 4.14. He ſaid to the Nobles and Rulers, and the reſt of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56068:11"/>the people, <hi>Bee not afraid of your Enemies;</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Lord which is great and terrible, and fight for your Brethren, your Sonnes, and your Daughters, your Wives and your Houſes. They were to fight for the Lord, whoſe cauſe was then in hand; and for the Common-wealth, and each mans private intereſſes: therefore ſaith he, <hi>Be not afraid of your Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, this ſheweth us, how direct a way it hath pleaſed the Lord herein to guide both Houſes of Parliament to walke in, <hi>viz.</hi> A way of undaunted courage and reſolution, as if they ſhould ſay to one another, as once thoſe <hi>Trojans,</hi> The onely way to ſafety to the Conquered, is to turne deſperate. Some may thinke they tranſgreſſe their limits; No, for how can they take leſſe courage to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, who being beſet behind and before with <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> and <hi>Ammonites,</hi> are to beſtirre themſelves for their people, and the Cities of their God. God and <hi>England,</hi> and every Shire and Citie in <hi>England,</hi> doe this day cry out unto them, ſaying; <hi>Bee ſtrong and of a good courage, be not afraid, neither be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed; for the Lord your God is with you whither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever you goe.</hi> Therefore let us not onely have high thoughts of them, and ſuch as are alwayes Honourable, but magnifie the Lord who hath put ſuch reſolutions into them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, let theſe words of <hi>Joab</hi> ſound in our eares this day. <hi>Be of good courage, and let us play the men for our people, and for the Cities of our God.</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:56068:11"/>Beloved! I cannot but look upon the Churches in this Land this day, as upon ſo many ſeverall Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or bands of Souldiers lying in ambuſh here under the fearn and bruſhet of the Wildernes, like the lyers in wait beſide <hi>Gibeah,</hi> againſt the wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed rebellious <hi>Benjamites.</hi> I know wee are little dreamt of at this time in any part of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, our weapons being as inviſible to the eye of fleſh, as our perſons are to all the world. So much the better; we ſhall fight this day with the greater ſafety to our ſelves, and danger to our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; among whom, I am confident in the Lord, thouſands ſhall fall, and never know who hurt them. We arrogate nothing to our ſelves; for if the weapons of our warfare are mighty, it is not through us, but through God. But if the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God would have thought of a way of quickeſt diſcomfiture to the adverſary, what courſe could they have taken better, then to have divided their Forces, and to have ſent ſome to lye in wait in the wilderneſſe, to come upon the backs of Gods Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies with deadly Faſtings and Prayer, murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers that will kill point blanke from one end of the world to the other. Here then is our ſtation, therefore <hi>be we of good courage, and let us play the men at this time;</hi> and firſt, For our God. For he is ours, Beloved, and we truſt he is <hi>Englands:</hi> and ſhall we ſee our ſelves bereft of him? Can the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God endure to ſee Idols and Idolothites to ſtand in his place, and <hi>Dagon</hi> to bee exalted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the <hi>Arke?</hi> If <hi>Iſrael</hi> be robbed of their God,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56068:12"/>what have they more? What are the people, or Cities, if they bee not the people and Cities of our God? They are even like the world without the Sun. God therefore and Religion lie at ſtake; and therefore <hi>let us play the men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, Gods worſhip lyeth engaged: all the pure and unmixt Ordinances of CHRIST JESUS call for helpe this day. The Word of God lifteth up its voice this day unto us, like a baniſhed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine; O how have I been abuſed by the corrupt Gloſſes of theſe moderne <hi>Phariſees?</hi> How have the Scriptures beene wreſted? The Word pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned in Pulpits? Chriſt fought againſt, with the word of his owne mouth? Doctrines of Devils maintained with pretence of Scripture? The Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of Chriſt perſecuted and hunted like Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triges upon the Mountaines; for holding ſorth the Word in his native luſtre? O deliver the Word of God out of this Captivity! The Seales of righteouſneſſe cry alowd to us this day; They crave reduction to the rules of the Goſpell. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Ordinance pleads for vindication, travelling in paine under the captivity of beggarly Rudiments. O, ſay they, we have been dealt forth theſe many ſcores of yeares under Goſpell-light, in ſuch ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome formes, that men abhorre <hi>the offerings of the Lord.</hi> Oh! The Whoore hath quaffed, and made herſelfe drunke with her Pandors, and Paramours, and with her cunning and uncleane Merchants, <hi>in the veſſell of the Lords Sanctuary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beloved! Let us hold; and heare no more of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56068:12"/>theſe ſad complaints; for who can have pitic, and patience too? Have we the blood of Proteſtants in us? Doth the ſpirit of JESUS runne in our veines? It is enough: We cannot want <hi>courage,</hi> nor but <hi>play the men</hi> for God and pure Religion. And if any people under the Sunne, who more then we, whom the gracious hand of heaven hath aſſerted from that ſpirituall bondage, under which we once did groane? It is a truth, we ſaw but litle in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of what now we doe, when we left our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive homes; as much it is not that yet we ſee, tho, bleſſed be the Lord for what we doe. But is there any people in the world who have taſted more of the ſweet of God, and Chriſt, and Ordinances, then we in this Land have done? Doe any know the price of God and Chriſt, more then wee here? I beſeech you in the Lord, Conſider, and let the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt riſe in you at this inſtant, and wreſtle and ſtrive this day in Prayer; let us looſe a joynt with <hi>Iacob,</hi> but we will be <hi>Iſraelites</hi> this day. Let us play the men according to the knowledge, fence and experience that we have of God and Chriſt. Let us halt to our dying day, but we will returne laden with the ſpoile of Rebels.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as Gods worſhip lieth ingaged, ſo <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> by conſequence his Name; And what ſaith <hi>Ioſhua</hi> to God upon the day of afflicting his ſoule? <hi>What ſhall be done to thy great Name?</hi> When the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Lord were to weep between the Porch and the Altar upon the day of their faſting, they were to ſay, <hi>Spare thy people, O Lord, and give not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56068:13"/>thine heritage to reproach, that the heathen ſhould rule over them;</hi> wherefore ſhould they ſay among the people, <hi>Where is their God?</hi> Then will the Lord be jealous for his Land, and pitty his people, as it followeth. And ſhall not this argument then move us, which ever prevailed with the Lord? <hi>Moſes, Joſhua,</hi> the Prieſts, no ſooner urge Gods glory, but the Lord anſwereth them.</p>
            <p>Oh! how then hath Gods honour been layd in the duſt by thoſe Prelates, who now with their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours begin to lye there themſelves? What in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultings have they uſed? What triumphes have they often led? And as if they had bound our Chriſt like <hi>Sampſon,</hi> and put him to grind in the Priſon houſe (as in ſome ſence they have.) Oh! how have theſe Lords of the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> gathered themſelves together to offer ſacrifice to their <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,</hi> to burne Incenſe to their Drag, to their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, their Policies, Prelacies, Confederacies, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurations, Superſtitions, and ſo rejoyce? Saying, <hi>Our God hath delivered Chriſt our enemy into our hand,</hi> the deſtroyer of our Prelacies, who ſlew many of us.</p>
            <p>And thus, could they but get the day again, they would ſay, and <hi>Dagon</hi> ſhould up as high, and CHRIST be throwne downe as low, as ever. And can we endure ſo much as the thought of it? The Lord forbid. O <hi>let us play the men</hi> for our God, and our Chriſt, whoſe glory is more worth then ten thouſand worlds of ſoules. O let us ſet to it this day with all our <hi>courage;</hi> let every veine, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56068:13"/>joynt, and limbe, and affection in us, pray this day; <hi>O Lord God, remember thine honour, wee pray thee, and ſtrengthen us, we pray thee, that we may once be avenged on theſe Philiſtims againſt their Lords; for our two eyes.</hi> Yea, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> ſaid, <hi>Let me dye with the Philiſtims:</hi> So, let us dye with theſe <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtims,</hi> if need were. Let us kill our ſelves with faſting and prayer, to deſtroy them, and to pull downe the Temple of their <hi>Dagon,</hi> all the fabrick of the <hi>Hyrarchie,</hi> upon the heads of theſe ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prelates.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let us conſider how inglorious a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> is without God. <hi>when the Arke was captiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the glory was departed from Iſrael.</hi> The Ark was the teſtimony of Gods preſence; ſo that when God doth not teſtifie his preſence with a People, <hi>they are without glory.</hi> If the World bee beautified by the preſence of the Sun, ſo great glory attend the Court where the King is reſident: How doth the ſpecial preſence of the Prince of the Kings of the earth, beautifie that Land where it is? Yea, there is not onely a ſpirituall glory, viſible onely to a ſpirituall eye, reſulting from the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall preſence of the Lord among a people; but alſo an externall, and viſible glory. When <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaphat</hi> walked in the firſt waies of his Father <hi>David,</hi> and lift up his heart in the waies of the Lord; and that a great Reformation was wrought in the Land, and that he had ſpread the Word all over his kingdome; it is ſaid, <hi>That hee had riches and honour in aboundance;</hi> and <hi>The feare of the Lord
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56068:14"/>fell upon all Kingdoms of the Lands that were round about Iudah, ſo that they made no warre againſt</hi> Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſhaphat. Yea, the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> and <hi>Arabians</hi> brought him great preſents, inſomuch that <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaphat</hi> waxed great exceedingly, and hee built in <hi>Iudah,</hi> Caſtles, and Cities of ſtore; and hee had much buſineſſe in the Cities of <hi>Iudah;</hi> and the men of Warre, mighty men of valour, were in <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</hi> So that <hi>Iudah</hi> had aboundance of exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall glory, even the glory of riches, and honour, and power, and greatneſſe, and peace, and homage from forreigne States, and of great emploiments, and of mighty men of valour. Wherefore, ſeeing God is come neerer to <hi>England,</hi> then formerly, and hath of late made ſuch gracious tenders of himſelfe, and hath found better acceptance then formerly; O let us conclude in dayly prayer, and this day eſpecially, for his preſence to be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and more cleerely manifeſted then ever. For if he ſhould now withdraw againe, wee are to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect no glory to reſt among them. You know how little honour hath been viſible in that Land of late yeares; It hath for a long time beene a Land of ſorrow, of mourning, and not of joy and rejoyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. It hath not been called <hi>Naomi,</hi> but <hi>Marah;</hi> it hath not been a Crowne of Glory, nor a Royall Diadem in the hand of the Lord; but been termed for ſaken and deſolate. But now the day hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne to dawne, yea, the Sunne ſeemes to be riſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n on it, if it ſtrike nor in againe, and a Tempeſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue upon it; which the Lord forbid. O why ſhould
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56068:14"/>we give the Lord any reſt, till it be called <hi>Hephzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bah,</hi> and <hi>Beulah, My delight is in her, becauſe ſhe is marryed to the Lord.</hi> For when once a Land is joyned to the Lord, hee is married to it, and then his delight is in it, and hee will cloath it with honour and glory. And thus much for the firſt ground of the Exhortation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the other is the State and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> which lye ingaged; our people, and our Cities. Even Politick Priviledges are of weighty conſequence, and moment. But in what a way, both people and Cities in that Land, have beene dealt with for many yeares paſt, we need ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, when it is clearely repreſented to the view of the whole world in the late Remonſtrance of the ſtate of that Kingdome. When men judge un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly, and accept the perſons of the wicked, and rid not the poore and needy out of the hand of the wicked, nor do juſtice to the afflicted; when they will not know, nor underſtand, but walke on in darkeneſſe; what followeth? <hi>All the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Land are out of courſe, Pſal.</hi> 82.5. The Heavens, Sea, and dry Land have been ſhaken, and there hath been both a Church-quake, and a State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake in that Land, which hath removed Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſwallowed up both people and Cities. For when Foundations are not onely ſhaken, but out of courſe, and removed, what have people, and Cities to ſtand upon? There is no man in ſuch a caſe, who can ſay, I ſtand upon ſure ground, I feare
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56068:15"/>no colours, I am able to beare out my juſt actions. For if they ſhould ſay, we will have recourſe to our Foundations; alas, they are out of Courſe, they are removed, and none knowes where to find them.</p>
            <p>Beloved! It is a fearefull thing to have but the foundation of an houſe undermined, the corner ſtones removed, and the pillars pulled downe; but when whole Cities, and Townes, and Shires of people, ſhall be undermined, and neere blown up, oh how dreadfull is it? When a People who can ſay, <hi>We are Romans, neither did we buy our freedom, but are the lawfull and legitimate heires of Liberty, ſhall be ſcourged uncondemned;</hi> and when Cities that were formerly Cities of Refuge, where the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted might find ſuccour under municipall Laws, ſhall be invaded by deſtroyers; what cauſe have men to doe as <hi>David</hi> and his followers, when they had recourſe to <hi>Ziklag,</hi> thinking to have found ſhelter there; but loe, the Citie was burnt, and their wives, and ſons, and daughters taken Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives? <hi>Even lift up their voices and weepe, untill they have no more power to weepe.</hi> When a man may ſay as <hi>David; In the way wherein I walked, they privily laid a ſnare for me: I looked on my right hand, and behold, there was no man would know mee, refuge failed me:</hi> this is miſerable. For a man thinkes himſelfe ſafe in his way, and if he be in the Kings high way, he thinks much to have a ſnare laid for him; and none but Cutters will way lay a man there. For <hi>Edom</hi> to aſſault <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56068:15"/>promiſed to walke on, only <hi>in the Kings high way; O barbarous and inhumane! Numb.</hi> 20, 17, 20. But when a man ſhall be aſſaulted in ſuch a caſe, and he looks on his right hand, and on his left for help, and can ſee none, then his purſe, if not his throat is indangered. Surely it is uncomfortable travelling in ſuch Countries.</p>
            <p>Brethren! Liberty is more precious then life, inaſmuch as death is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon lot of all men, but ſervitude the portion only of men deſtined to miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And if a people be ſold for bondmen, and bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women, what can countervaile the Kings damage? And ſeldome is it, that cruelty reſts ſatisfied with bondage, but makes his progreſſions to further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of blood. When people &amp; Cities cannot ſay <hi>Municipia,</hi> but <hi>Man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ipia,</hi> what remaines but death; as when the <hi>Ephramites</hi> could not pronounce <hi>Shib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boleth,</hi> but onely <hi>Sibboleth,</hi> preſently they dyed for it. If goods and liberty be in the power of mens wills, why not alſo life? There is much compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in people and Cities, even all that is Politick, Oeconomick, or Private; but I inſtance onely in the greateſt miſchiefe. Let us therefore uſe the words of Queene <hi>Heſter</hi> vnto <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them unto God. <hi>If we have found favour in thy ſight, O Lord, and if it pleaſe the King, let our lives be given us at our petition, and our people at our requeſt; for our people are ſold to bee deſtroyed, and ſlaine, and periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any ſay, How are we concerned in the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of other men, ſo long as we are free. I ſay, It
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56068:16"/>toucheth us, as <hi>Lots</hi> captivity touched <hi>Abraham,</hi> who muſtred up his men, and took his confederats along with him, <hi>Mamre, Eſhcol,</hi> and <hi>Aner,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered him out of bondage. And if we forbeare to deliver them that are drawne unto death, and thoſe that are ready to be ſlaine; if wee ſay, <hi>we knew it not</hi> or <hi>what did it concerne us? He that pondereth the heart confidereth it, and hee will render unto us according to our workes. Prov.</hi> 24.11.12. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Let us play the men for our people and Cities.</hi> What though it be well with us? <hi>Let us yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the afflictions of</hi> Joſeph; yea, and the words of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> Butler; <hi>Thinke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me when it ſhall be well with thee; and ſhew kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, I pray thee, unto me, and make mention of mee unto Pharaoh, and bring me out of this houſe.</hi> For thus in effect ſpeaks <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> to us this day, and all the Cities in them; now that it is well with you, think upon us, and ſhew kindneſſe unto us, and make mention of us unto the God of heaven, that we may fully once be delivered out of the houſe of bondage. Oh, ſaith ſuch and ſuch a Citie, there are ſo many thouſand ſoules in me, who cannot diſcerne between the right hand and the left.</p>
            <p>But if it be not well with them, how can it bee well with us? If the <hi>Arke,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Iudah,</hi> abide in tents, and the people of God are encamped in the open fields, what comfort can we have in our houſes, food, or wives? What though we are ſo farre from them in place? The needle in the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56068:16"/>Compaſſe is never quiet till it pointeth to the North, at a thouſand times greater diſtance. Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions touched with grace, ſtand firme from one end of the World to the other. <hi>Nehemiah's</hi> heart ſtood right towards <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when he was in <hi>Perſia;</hi> and though hee was not in an humbling Wilderneſſe, but an alluring Pallace, even in <hi>Shuſhan,</hi> yet <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> came into his minde. For when <hi>Hanani,</hi> and certaine men of <hi>Iudah</hi> came thither to him, he asked them concerning his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren that were left of the Captivity, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> And when they told him of the great affliction and reproach, he ſate downe and wept, and mourned many daies, <hi>and faſted and prayed before the God of Heaven, Neh.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3, &amp;c. Wherefore let that Word of the Lord ſound of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in our eares; <hi>Ye that have eſcaped the Sword, go away, ſtand not ſtill; remember the Lord a farre off, and let</hi> Ieruſalem <hi>come into your minds. Ier.</hi> 50.51. And though we have but a day, or two, wherein to joyne all our Forces in the Land together, and to give the Adverſaries a broad ſide; Yet let us now and then make excurſions by our ſelves in private, now that the Lord cals for help againſt the Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Are we not all the Voluntarie of IESUS, whoſe People ſhall be willing in the day of his power? neither is there any reſtraint unto the Lord, to ſave by many, or by few; by whole Churches, or by ſingle perſons. Let us therefore be often ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturing by our ſelves, like <hi>Ionathan</hi> and his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour-bearer againſt the <hi>Philiſtims.</hi> If ever we af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56068:17"/>our ſoules, let it be in theſe daies; for we may partly underſtand by Bookes the number of the yeares which God will accompliſh in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> So that, we ſet our faces unto the Lord God, to ſeek by Prayer and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, with Faſting, Sack cloth, and Aſhes. There is at this time a great battell between <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi> and the <hi>Dragon,</hi> and the <hi>Angels.</hi> The Beaſt and the Kings of the earth, and their Armies have gathered themſelves together to make warre with the Lambe. All the Principalities, and Powers, and Rulers of the Darkneſſe of the World, and Spirituall wickedneſſes in High places, are up in Armes this day, and there is ſcarce a Devill left behind in Hell. If ever therefore, now <hi>Let us quit our ſelves like men;</hi> the weapons of our Warre-fare are not Carnall, but mighty through God. Let us pray againſt them, as <hi>Moſes</hi> againſt <hi>Amalek;</hi> and Preach againſt them, as the Prieſts under the Law, when the Hoſt went out againſt the Enemy; and ſing againſt them, as <hi>Iehoſophat</hi> and the men of <hi>Iudah</hi> did againſt <hi>Moah, Ammon,</hi> and <hi>Edom;</hi> and live againſt them, as it is written, <hi>When the Hoſt goeth forth againſt the Enemy, then keepe thee from every wicked thing. Deut.</hi> 23.9. Every Ordinance of God is a deadly murtherer. O let us walke and ſleep in our Armour and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be unfurniſhed of promiſes touching the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of <hi>Babel,</hi> and her builders. Let the cauſe of God affect us deeply, and the people and Cities of our God be alwaies in our eyes. And let the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56068:17"/>deſolations of Chriſtendome awaken us to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Prayers, and conſtant ſympathy; and the bloud of Gods people (particularly) in <hi>Ireland,</hi> be to us as the bloud of Grapes and Mulberies are to Elephants, to provoke them to fight. Oh thoſe incarnate <hi>Iriſh</hi> Devils! let them be often in our ſight. Their blaſphemies, their burnings, their robberies, their rapes, their roſtings, their ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings, rippings, hangings, drownings, diſ-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brings, butcheries, the very ſhambles of the Devil erected in <hi>Ireland,</hi> would be alwaies in our eyes and eares. And yet when we have done all, let us referre the iſſue to the Almighty, ſaying; <hi>Let the Lord do what ſeemeth him good.</hi> The laſt thing, is their reſigning up their wills into the hands of GOD; whereof a few words, and I end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioab</hi> is not wanting in the uſe of all meanes to obtaine victory, yet lookes above them, and refers the iſſue to the Lord of Hoſts; teaching us, <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To neglect no meanes of Victorie, yet to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon the Lord onely for a gracious iſſue.</p>
            <p>For there is no truſting in our bows or ſwords, it is the Lord that ſaveth us from our enemies. It is not the race to the ſwift, for then <hi>Ioab</hi> knew that his brother <hi>Aſael</hi> had not dyed by the hand of <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi> Neither is it the battel to the ſtrong, for then he knew, that <hi>Goliah</hi> ſhould never have fallen by the hand of <hi>David. The Horſe is prepared againſt the day of Battell, but victory is of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:56068:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſc.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, Let this teach us to ſeeke the Lord, that none of this may ever reſt upon the arme of fleſh, nor number the people; as once <hi>David</hi> did. Hee had a Catalogue of all the mighty men, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. and now too, he will have a liſt of all the Souldiers in his Kingdome, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. He Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized the carnall ſtrength of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred not the Word of the Lord, which ſaid, <hi>When thou takeſt the ſumme of the children of Iſrael, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their number, then they ſhall give every man a ranſome for his ſoule unto the Lord, that there bee no plague among them, when thou numbreſt them. Exod.</hi> 30.12. Let us remember <hi>England</hi> in this particular; It lyeth under great temptations to this kind of Idolatry. The Union of the two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, two Houſes, all (or moſt) of the Shires by Petitioning for Reformation, the ſetling of the Warrefare of the Kingdome at Sea and Land, the mervellous wiſdome, and undaunted reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Parliament, their ſucceſſe in many matters, the eyes of many on them, and the applauſe that is given them, beſides whatſoever other tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and armes of fleſh; may ſoone ſolicite the hearts, even of the godly, much more of others, to carnall confidence, that they may never lift up their eyes unto the hilles from whence commeth their helpe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Siſera, Midian, Goliah, Senacherib, Zerah,</hi> fall by their carnall props; when <hi>Barak, Gedeon, David, Jonathan,</hi> and <hi>Aſa,</hi> reſting upon the Lord
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56068:18"/>in the uſe of ſmall meanes, returne victorious. Two dayes weeping &amp; faſting was little enough for the eleven Tribes to gaine the day of <hi>Benjamin.</hi> O let not Gods people reſt in Councell, Number, Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, Ammunition, but <hi>in the Lord of Hoſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Let not us then place any affiance in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> our Faſting daies, but refer al to God when we have ended them. If the Devill cannot make us convert our Prayers unto Idols; he will ſee whether hee cannot convert them into Idols.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Let us lay our hearts this day in the Lords hand, as once <hi>Eli</hi> &amp; <hi>Hezekiah</hi> being threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as here <hi>Ioab</hi> ready for the onſet, did. The People of God, both in old <hi>England</hi> and new, have waited on his providence both by earthly and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly meanes. <hi>Now let the Lord doe what ſeemeth him good.</hi> If it ſhall ſeem good to him, that <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Ireland,</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſhall ſuffer yet further, the will of the Lord be done. What remaineth, but for us to magnifie Gods juſtice, and to put our mouthes into the duſt? Eſpecially, (as for <hi>England</hi>) conſidering how long the Prelacie hath fought againſt Chriſt, and kept him out of his Kingdome: What bloody brazen-faced Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries have bin committed there? What Atheiſmes, Blaſphemies, Adulterie, Prodigies of pride, grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of faces, ſelling of the Poore, countenanced Sabbath breakers, deriſion of holineſſe, ſhedding the blood of the Saints, have been common in that Land; and in a ſpeciall manner, conſidering the ſinnes of Gods deare people there, particularly of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56068:19"/>his Meſſengers in their lon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> continued ſubjection unto the power of Antichriſt, in the Prelacy, the warpings and ſhrinkings of ſome, the fearefulnes and cowardize of many (for which, for mine own particular, I deſire to be humbled while I live) the reading of that abominable Booke of curſed liberty, contributing to the Superſtitious Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſneſſe of <hi>Paules,</hi> and to the raiſing of Forces againſt the <hi>Scots,</hi> (a dreadfull bloody ſin) reading, or permitting to be read, Proclamations, and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the Churches againſt them. I ſay, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all this (to mention no more) though we have uſed what meanes we can, and though they ſhould doe the like, yet let our expectations of ſucceſſe be low, let us humbly ſubmit our ſelves to the will of the Lord, ſaying; <hi>Let him doe what ſeemeth him good.</hi> If it ſeem good to him to pardon the Land, O bleſſed be ſuch gentleneſſe; If otherwiſe it ſeem good to him to correct it, bleſſed bee his juſtice. What ſoever he doth, is good; therefore let him doe it. And any mercy at any time, is enough for great tranſgreſſors.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
